Hello. Today we're going to try to find
out if the service class is a good place
to put and hold the business logic.
Okay. So let's start by seeing what are
we going to cover today. We're going to
start by seeing some real life examples
of ways that I saw
implementing business logic into
different places. Okay. After that we
are going to try to see and understand
what are the difficulties which these
kind of approaches.
Before that because I'm not here only to
blame. We're going to see what would be
my proposal to approach these kind of
things. Okay.
After that we're going to see some code
examples on how do I implement this.
Okay.
After that we are going to recap some of
the benefits that this approach brings
to the table. Finally, we're going to
see how we can move into a magnificent
future.
Okay,
enough chitchat.
Let's start by seeing some real life
example
on managing business logic.
First of all, and I think you all will
be pretty familiarized with this is
oversized rotors. These will be
functions with a lot of mixed things
between them like business logic,
thirdparty services, deep interactions,
error handling and a bunch of logging.
Okay.
Second example, single single class with
the same thing, a single class with a
bunch of different responsibilities all
over the place. H it's maybe a better
step. It's easier to move a single class
into another project than move the
routers with all the things that are
pretty tight to the implementation of
the framework that you are using. So,
and lastly, the functional approach all
the same things but all separate
functions scatter all over the place.
This is the one that is most difficult
for me. I'm not saying functional
approach to the things are bad but
usually tend to make a lot of of mess
when you are start creating
util function here another function
there h it's a mess. Now let's move to
start seeing what are the difficulties
with these kind of approaches. Okay,
first of all, no single approach, no
consistency on code. Working on each
service feels like riding a bike in a
totally different way. Okay, it's pretty
difficult to test the business logic
without getting a mix of dependencies
involved and running into a lot of
rabbit holes through that. Okay. Also,
this tends to make pretty hard to find
and isolate the business logic that we
are trying to put on the code. As you
can imagine, this turns into difficult
situations when we are trying to on
board new people to the team when we are
trying to debug under a severity or when
you are trying to work with some code
that you are not familiarized with.
Okay, I know that same things it's
easier to implement them. I know that
you're gonna make the goat thinking that
it's going to go to one place and be
used in one way and there it's going to
evolve into different ways.
But there is a lot of things that we can
do in order to make our life easier when
those kind of things happen. So this is
trying to help you go around those
things in an easier way. So let's start
by seeing what will be my proposal.
We're going to need to start by
separating the code into different
classes with different purposes.
Again, let's try to understand what is
the main function. What is the main
thing that a class has to do? if it's
going to take advantage or of a specific
library to do things like interacting
with database like interacting with API
services like parsing some data like
doing some business analysis
like scrapping things we need to
understand what are the main languages
that they are going to use what are the
things that are related with them and we
need to separate those in order to have
classes that just one thing and that is
easier to understand. If we have all the
things mix it, we're going to end up
losing the trail to that and the testing
will be pretty heavier. Okay, so
one class to interact with each database
object. This will be an example. We're
going to have one class that is going to
talk with the client
table that it's going to have the all
workounds. Okay, it's going to use SQL
Alchemy, Django or RM or whatever you
are using, but it's going to have some
things tied there to that specific
table. One class per third party service
that we are interacting with. If we are
talking with let's say four or five
different APIs because we need to get
data from a lot of places or do a lot of
things, each separate API should have
their own class. Okay, why? because they
will
um because they will maybe ask different
login, they will have different headers,
they will have different kind of
responding for to errors. So we are
going to need to prepare the things and
talk the same language into each
separate class. This will allow us to
make contract testing to have the field
separate to also mock the things in a
nice way when we need to do test and to
have all the things into one place.
Okay.
Try to use the single responsibility
principle. This is more or less what I
was trying to say h before.
Finally, I like to have one class to
group them all and hold the business
logic. Okay, this will mean like how do
I I what do we I expect when I call to
uh this API? What do I do when I call
this API? How do I process the data? How
do I save the data? What do I do with
that data? This class should use the
other classes to give orders and give
and say how we are going to do the
things and you're going to read this fun
the functions from this class like a
textbook and you are going to understand
hopefully
how the business logic is implemented.
Okay.
So some good practices use dependency
injection single responsibility
principle client pattern repository
pattern write understandables names for
functions. This is a pretty spicy topic
but please please try to do that. I want
to understand what this function is
doing and then if I want to know more I
can go inside that. If I go to a
function that says get client or get
prices and I go up there and it return
prices, client
amount of sales,
those are different things and should
have their own place.
And finally, we will need one ring to
room them all. As I say earlier,
some extra tips,
use single public functions for the
principle action. What is this? This is
if you have a class that is pretty
complex and is use a lot of functions to
build the functionality that you have.
Try to use sub functions and only expose
as a public or without underscore at the
starting Python.
the main function that the people is
going to be needing or that it's going
to be using. Okay,
if you build a class that is pretty
complex to use, use a factory method.
We're going to see an example of this uh
after
delegate complexity into subprivate
method. But again, don't go too deep.
Let's make an example. You have the
service class that it's the one that is
going to use the client that is one for
the API that is the one that is going to
use the repository to save the data that
is going to use another class to parse
and process the information. Okay, good.
You are going to have on that class one
function that is going to be the one
exposing the functionality and then that
function is going to have the usage of
the different functions of the class.
If you go into
those classes, you could find one more
layer of deepness. Okay? Only one sub
method could be multiple, but with no
sub method inside of those methods. Why?
Because if you start going deeper and
deeper and deeper, you're going to
become crazy going from function into
function. And this is not good. Try to
do it. It's not always possible but try
to leave all in the first layer. Okay,
in the service class and all the other
classes that you are trying to build.
Also, each class should have their own
separate test file. This could be used
as I say here as a way of documenting
the class. How is it worked? What are
the things that are dependent on? How
these sub functions works? what is doing
specifically this function? What is the
input and the output? This is pretty
important.
Also, try to not abuse patterns or
principles. There are no silver ballots.
Okay.
Lastly, be happy. Yay.
Let's go and see some real code. This is
the code that I make to make an audit
into my internet service provider. Okay.
So, first of all, we're going to have
the internal connection log service.
This is going to be the class that
expose the whole functionality. This
class is going to have two functions.
Lock the internet connection for single
servers and log the internet connection
for multiple servers. Okay.
This class is going to be composed by
the parser, the gateway and the
repository.
The gateway is the one that is going to
be in charge to go and get me the
information. Okay.
The parser is going to be the one in
charge of transform that information.
And finally, the repository is going to
be the one in charge of saving that
information. What are some of the things
that this approach brings to the table?
Let's put for example the speed test
JSON repository. Right now I'm using a
JSON. I don't need to use a database. I
don't need to use I could use a CSV
whatever I want to save that
information. I'm going to give one
object to these things to this
repository and I want that repository to
save that information. Today it's going
to be a JSON. Tomorrow could be a
database. But all the logic on how do I
save the information?
It's up to the repository. I don't care.
I as a service don't care. The only
thing that I care is that it saves my
information. So I could change that to a
separate s service that have the name
the same uh functions exposed and
gets the same information and returns
the same information. All the
implementation is down to the
repository. Okay.
Now let's see another example. Let's say
we have the speed test getway. Right now
I'm getting the information with um
library that get this information. I
could get it in another way. I can do it
in another way. It doesn't matter for
me. The only thing that I want is that I
could be sure that I will get the same
information and I could then parse this
information. Okay, that's our important
thing. So in this way I could switch
these parts from the main class and make
it work in the same way but with
different things. Okay.
Now
let's take a look to the service here.
As you may see I'm importing all the
things. I'm using this to inject the
dependencies.
Okay. And I have the log internet
connection for single server. I don't
return anything because I don't need to.
But what do I do? I get the speed test
output. Output. How do I do that? By
calling the client to get the speed test
result. I want to know I need to know
right now what do I do with that? How do
I do that? No, I afterwards need to know
that I parse that output. Okay, I log
the things and finally I save this. This
is pretty simple thing. After that, I
have another function to do this for
multiple servers and it's an easy a PC
implementation. Okay, but here I know
that this doesn't have a pretty complex
business logic.
But if this were more complex, I will be
able to see this and read this in an
easy way. Finally, as I say, if this
class turns to complex, and in this
case, we have three different classes
that compose this. For me, that is
complex. I can just have a build
function that returns an instance for
this. Okay, this is this is easy. So,
let's go one layer deeper. Let's see the
client. What does the client? I use the
sub process. I use some things here. I
create a data class so I could do some
things and use these servers in another
places.
I need the server ID and then I have the
command that is pretty clear. I try to
check the process with this command and
then I try to parse this association.
Here is the other function.
Finally, if I get any error, I just
catch it and login. It doesn't matter. I
don't need to raise anything here
because I could continue doing this and
it's just one one error and that doesn't
impact in a highway the output that I
need. Okay,
then let's try to see the parser. Maybe
this is the more complex. Okay, again
here we have a data class with all the
informations that I need. This is to be
clear what are the things that we are
going to return. the download of the
speed, the shooter, the bandwidth, all
the things. Okay. And I have a way to do
this as I did. And then you see that I
use a JSON and I return a speed test
paret output. This is important if I
want to change the repository. Okay, why
this is important? Because if I want to
change the repository, I will need to be
able to process this into the SQL
database, the CSP or whatever. But I
will be working with this. This will be
like the contract that we have between
classes. Okay.
Well, first here is how we parse the
output. We have the server info. We have
the result info, the resulting phone.
And we parse this here.
And then we just start to download the
things and do all the things that we
need. We transform the D data. We go
from bytes to megabytes here. H we also
do that here. We do with the ping. We
don't do that. And we start getting all
the information that we have here. As
you may see, we have some helper
functions or sub functions that are here
to do some complex things that I use
more than once in this main loop. Okay,
so for me it was good to put this here
and don't expose this to the service
because the service doesn't care on how
do I go from bytes to megabytes.
This thing only cares about I give the
things on megabytes. Okay. And also I
get this erh on another place because I
get this current time and I'm using this
a lot in different places and it's
pretty tight to the kind of information
that I get but it doesn't care to the
service that is the class that is using
the only thing that those service want
is the parse output
to be more clear let's say that I could
put this some of this on the service and
start calling functions here that will
be doing those kind of things. For
example, I could say a function that
says, hey, parse the uh download, parse
the upload, parse the ping, and putting
that that would be a different approach
is a valid approach. I took this one
that is maybe obscuring a little bit
more the things, but it's only one layer
deep. So for me it's not a big thing but
it's that is h for your team and the
people we are you are coding with to
discuss. Okay
nice. Now we are getting to the
repository. This is pretty simple. We
are using the internet log json. We are
saving this. We are getting the output.
We transform it into a dict and we are
just saving this. We are obtaining the
current file. We are updating the things
and we are returning true and if we find
some error in this case we return files
because again
not being able to save one time these
things is not a problem and this is just
a personal use case. Maybe if it was a
thing that we were doing for a company,
the error handling will be different.
But in this case, I just log an error
and whatever. Then I could check the
logs. Okay, here we have some helper
functions that is get the current file
and save this to a file. What? Why do I
did this in this way? I could put that
in the same in the first function. Yes,
but I like to do it in this way. it was
more clean and easier to read. Okay,
good. I hope this is somewhere clear to
you. I hope I really hope it is. And if
it's not, I invite you to check check
out the GitHub repository or contact me
and we can talk more about it.
Now, let's recap some of the benefits
that this approach brings to the table.
First of all, is easy to understand.
It's easy to read. It's easy to
understand how you are interacting with
each part of the logic with the
database, with the APIs, with the whole
combination of both
how you are parsing the information.
It's easy to read and it's all grouped
by separate responsibility. Okay,
it's easy to implement.
If you manage to make an agreement on
what are the things that one class is
going to pass to the other, you can
create test data. You can start building
all at the same time. You could have one
developer on each thing. one building
the interaction with the third party
service with the APIs, other saving the
data and another parsing the data
because you will have examples to use
and you could work freely at the same
time without tossing each other foots. H
there is not a lot of layers of code.
It's not that you are having things
under things under things. You are
trying to do the things in a concise way
and an explicit way. It's pretty easy to
test. Right here, I didn't show the
test, but you will have test for each
things and you will not need to mock a
lot of things unless you are testing the
service. And in that case, you should
have examples for all the other things
and you have a pretty clear
understanding on how those are working.
So, it's going to be easier for you to
test the things and you can develop in a
more confident way. Okay.
It's pretty easy to document. Also you
can have doctrine in the classes. You
can have things that talk about the same
thing. And if this is not enough,
let's see how we can move into a
magnificent future of code.
Full refactor you shall not pass. We are
going to make as we were Gandalf and we
are trying to avoid doing full refactors
to the thing. Okay, we're going to start
by thinking
what's the main responsibility that this
service have. First, good questions to
make. How can I separate the code into
quasive places?
Finally, agree with your team. If you
are trying to move from one kind of code
to the other or to do a refactor, you
need to agree with your team. You need
to understand that you are all going to
the same place because if not you are
going to write with the right hand and
you are going to erase that with the
left hand as we say here in Argentina.
You are going to start working in
something then someone is going to come
and going to start doing another thing
and this is okay. This is part of the
process from a team to consolidate the
practices that they have together. Okay.
But agree with your team.
Start small. move single and small
responsibilities at a time. Okay, let's
say we enter into a code mess. We are
going to do some things. We extract that
and we start moving one at a time. We
build classes along separate PRs. We add
unit test into each separate thing that
you are doing. This is one of the most
important things. If you don't have
test, you need to make the test to make
sure that the behavior that you used to
have is the same that you have right
now. Usually in the migrations or in the
refactors or however you want to call
it, the most difficult part is to
maintain the same functionality because
you end up doing things thinking you are
fixing things but you are changing the
functionality and that's bad. Okay. add
integration test to the full flow of
your code. This is another pretty
important thing
and once you realize you will be in a
much better place.
Thank you. Thanks. I really appreciate
you taking the time to hear me talking
about the things. Hope this really
helped you in some way. If you have
better ways to do this, just let me
know. We could talk about it and we
could all learn. Thank you and see you
in the next video.